Guide to the Foggy Bottom collection, 1907-1998 MS0868.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Foggy Bottom collection
1907-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Anderson, G. David
Combrinck, Laetitia
MS0868.UA
6 Linear Feet
The Foggy Bottom Collection is an outgrowth of the 1996 exhibit the Foggy Bottom Association and the Gelman Library sponsored called "Fantastic Foggy Bottom: The Growth of a Community." Materials in this collection include articles, building surveys, newspapers, books, photographs, slides, and artifacts. They range in date from 1907-98.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated to the University Archives by various members of the Foggy Bottom community.
Historical Note
The Foggy Bottom Collection is an outgrowth of the 1996 exhibit the Foggy Bottom Association and the Gelman Library sponsored called "Fantastic Foggy Bottom: The Growth of a Community." The exhibit was designed in conjunction with GW's 175th Anniversary, and a committee was formed to collect and choose materials for inclusion in the exhibit. Community members were asked to loan photographs, books, maps, and artifacts to the committee. A collection of the neighborhood newspaper, the "Foggy Bottom News" (1958-2004) was also donated to the collection as a result.
Although most materials loaned for exhibit were returned, photocopies of articles and news clippings, slides and copies of original photographs were made to keep for researchers to use. Future additions to the collection are planned, along with oral histories, which are hoped to be conducted by the University Archivist and volunteers.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include articles, building surveys, newspapers, books, photographs, slides, and artifacts. They range in date from 1907-98.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series.
Collection note
Various donors contributed to collection.
Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Churches -- Washington (D.C.); Maps; Buildings -- Washington (D.C.); Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); People; George Washington University--History
- Historic Foggy Bottom, 1923-1996; MS0868 Series 1; 2 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in this series include articles, building surveys, books and newspaper clippings documenting the history of Foggy Bottom. They range in date from 1923-96.
  - Foggy Bottom history-articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Foggy Bottom history-chapter of book "Washington at Home", undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Foggy Bottom history-street maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Foggy Bottom history-residents, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foggy Bottom history-Foggy Bottom Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Foggy Bottom history-Oldest Inhabitants of the District of Columbia, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foggy Bottom history-West End Citizen's Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foggy Bottom history-George Washington University, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Historic Foggy Bottom District/Historic Buildings, 1975 ca. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Building Surveys-Foggy Bottom Historic District (National Register of Historic Places), 1975 ca. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Buildings Surveys-Foggy Bottom/West End, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Buildings Surveys-George Washington University, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 79, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 80, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 81, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 103, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 104, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Buildings Surveys-Square 120, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Buildings-Watergate Complex, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Buildings-State Department, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Urban Renewal and Development: News clippings, 1923-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Urban Renewal and Development: News clippings, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Urban Renewal and Development: News clippings, 1959-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Urban Renewal and Development: News clippings, 1940-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Churches-Concordia United Church, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Churches-Liberty Baptist Church (originally on 23rd and I Streets, NW), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Churches-St. Mary's Episcopal Church, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Churches-St. Paul's Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Churches-Union United Methodist Church (20th St. NW, between H and I) - now a GWU building, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Churches-Western Presbyterian Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Walking Tours of Foggy Bottom, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Foggy Bottom 1800-1975: A Study in the Uses of an Urban Neighborhood" by Suzanne Sherwood (Box 3, Folder 5)
    General note
    2 copies
  - "Foggy Bottom: A Community in Search of Its Future"- GWU Department of Urban and Regional Planning, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book "Voices from the Field" by George Norris, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    History of National Association of Life Underwriters, which had building at 1922 F Street, NW (cited on pp.248-249)
  - Programs from exhibit "Fantastic Foggy Bottom", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Working drafts of text and layout for exhibit "Fantastic Foggy Bottom", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Loaned materials for use in "Fantastic Foggy Bottom" exhibit, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Union Methodist Episcopal Church: 1846 - Present," student paper by Alisa Rosen, 10/26/1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Acc#
    Originally Accession # 724.
- Photographs, 1907-1998; MS0868 Series 2; 4 Linear feet (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 5, Box 4)
  Materials in this series include photographs and slides of the Foggy Bottom area. They range in date from 1907-98.
  - Photographs: Whitehurst Freeway construction, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs: Whitehurst Freeway construction, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs: Whitehurst Freeway construction, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photographs: Foggy Bottom Festival, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: Foggy Bottom Festival, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Foggy Bottom misc., 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residences, 24th and F Street NW, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.1)
  - Photograph: Site of Pepco building, Penn Ave, NW, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.2)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residences, 25th and I Streets, NW, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.3)
  - Photograph: Quigley's Pharmacy, G Street, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.4)
  - Photograph: Maury Hall (left), undated (Box 4, Folder 18.5)
  - Photograph: Heurich brewery truck, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.6)
  - Photograph: S. Simon Tailor, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.7)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residents in front of Leo's Deli, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 18.8)
  - Photograph: Children, undated (Box 4, Folder 18.9)
  - Photograph: Mary Brown with siblings on steps of house on Virginia Ave across from present-day Watergate hotel, 1925 ca. (Box 4, Folder 18.1)
  - Photograph: SE corner of 20th and H Street, NW, looking toward 1912 H St., undated (Box 4, Folder 18.12)
  - Photograph: Virginia Ave., NW, Washington Gas Light Company tanks, 1920 ca. (Box 4, Folder 18.13)
  - Photograph: Park Central Hotel on S.E. corner of 18th and G Streets, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photograph: Site of World Bank building "E" at 701 19th St. NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photograph: Corner of New Hampshire Ave. and I St., NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photograph: After the renovation at 826 25th Street. NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photograph: 815 26th St. NW with son and brother of Mary Brown, 1946 ca. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photograph: Construction of D building on G Street, NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photograph: Washington Gas Light Company and West gas reservoir tank on Virginia and New Hampshire Avenues, 1920 ca. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photograph: G Street, near GW Deli, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photograph: I St. and New Hampshire Ave., NW, 1955 ca. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photograph: West corner of G and 18th Streets with Whelan Drugstore and Monmouth Hotel, 1960 ca. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photograph: Watergate Inn, Rock Creek Drive and F St., NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photograph: 2nd Western Presbyterian Church, H St., NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photograph: Constitution Ave. NW and 17th Street, NW, 1895 ca. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photograph: St. Mary's Church, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Photograph: Grant School, (School Without Walls High School), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photograph: Washington Circle, 23rd St. and Pennsylvania Ave., NW, 1948 ca. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Photograph: 1818 H Street, NW, 06/25/1946 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photograph: 23rd Street NW, looking south from I Street, 1938 ca. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Photograph: Church, 3 photos, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Construction of foundation and basement, Summer 1947; Choristers with Rev. Dr. Harding, 1888; Rubbish wagon cleaning the grounds of the church, March 1947
  - Photograph: Two people on G Street near the GW Deli, close to 22nd St., NW, 1945 ca. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Photograph: 19th and 20th Streets, NW site of Pepco building, 1970 ca. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Photograph: Near 25th and F Streets, NW, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Photograph: "Wink" Bill Coopes, G Street between 20th and 22nd Streets, NW, 1945 ca. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Photograph: G Street in front of Quigley's Pharmacy, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Photograph: Woodhull House, 1970 ca. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photograph: New York Avenue and 10th St, NW, 1945 ca. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photograph: St. Mary's congregation, 1960 ca. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photograph: St. Mary's congregation, 1945 ca. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photograph: State Department office, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Photograph: Two people in front of Quigley's Pharmacy on G Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photograph: Corner of 19th and F Streets, NW, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Site of World Bank building "H"
  - Photograph: Home of H. Randall Webb, 727 19th St. NW, built 1894, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photograph: H St. NW, home of boxer Marty Gallagher pictured, 1948 ca. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Photograph: 800 block of 26th Street and corner of Virginia Avenue, NW, 1948 ca. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photograph: State Department, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photograph: Site of World Bank's E Building, 701 19th St., NW, 1961 ca. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Photograph: Union Fire House, built 1832, meeting hall of the Association of the Oldest Inhabitants of D.C., undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Photograph: St. Mary's congregation, 1940 ca. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Photograph: St. Mary's congregation, 1960 ca. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Photograph: Hazel Handback and her father in front yard, State Department site in background, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Photograph: Houses on site of Western Presbyterian Church, 1908 H St., NW, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Photograph: Houses on site of Western Presbyterian Church, 1908 H St., undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Photograph: Sunday School class at Western Presbyterian Church, 1911 H St., 1925 ca. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Photograph: Buildings A, B, D, F, corner of 19th and H Streets, NW, 1980 ca. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Photograph: Theater group at Western Presbyterian Church, 1911 H St., NW, 1930 ca. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Photograph: Residence of Peter Hagner, 1812 H St., NW, 1910 ca. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Photograph: Original World Bank and IMF site, 19th and H Streets, NW, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Photograph: Home of H. Randall Webb, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Site of first IMF and World Bank E building, 727 19th St., NW
  - Photograph: 17th and New York Ave., NW, 1865 ca. (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Photograph: Aerial view of Virginia and New Hampshire Avenues, shows Potomac Plaza Apartments and GW Hospital, 1960 ca. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Photograph: Dance at GW, 1950 ca. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Photograph: Group of young men of the steps of the Grant School, 1945 ca. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Photograph: Sunday School class of St. Mary's church, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Photograph: Aerial view of Virginia Avenue towards Foggy Bottom, 1894 ca. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Photograph: View of Foggy Bottom and Georgetown from the Washington Monument, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Photograph: 20th St. between G and H Streets, NW, 1940 ca. (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Photograph: 2129 New York Avenue, NW, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Hazel Hanback standing on running board of car
  - Photograph: New Hampshire Ave., NW looking toward Watergate and Kennedy Center, 1980 ca. (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Photograph: Roof of Hattie M. Strong Hall for Women, GWU, 1940 ca. (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Photograph: Brown family at Titanic Memorial, site of Kennedy Center, 1946 ca. (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Photograph: Park Central Apartments, now Thurston Hall, 1900 F St. NW, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Photograph: Mrs. J. C. Brecht and Captain J. C. Brecht, 1904 ca. (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Photograph: Aerial View of Foggy Bottom looking south from Washington Circle, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - T-shirt: "I Love GW Students", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Worn by Olga Corey, longtime Foggy Bottom resident and activist (added to collection Feb. 2002)
  - Photograph: St. Rose's Industrial School for girls, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photograph: Peter Houses on 2618 K Street, NW, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photograph: Newly reconstructed Whitehurst Freeway, rebuilt from 1995-1998, 1998 ca. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photograph: Mr. & Mrs. Brewster at Fall Festival, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photograph: Briggs Elementary School, 22nd & E Streets NW, Federal Works Agency, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Etching
  - Photograph: Western Presbyterian Church at 1911 H Street, NW, 1855-1931, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photograph: Houses along 19th Street going toward G Street, NW, 04/15/1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    View from the 6th floor looking south, site of IMF building
  - Photograph: At the "Watergate" on the Waterfront behind the Lincoln Memorial, 1950 ca. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photograph: Young men on the steps of the Grant School, 1935 ca. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photograph: St. Paul's Episcopal Church, 1948 ca. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Photograph: Residents in front of the Virginia Apartments on G Street, NW, 1945 ca. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Photograph: Quigley's Pharmacy at 21st Street, NW, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photograph: Virginia Ave. and 25th Street, NW, ca. 1925 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Photograph: Dorothy Baines and Peggy Cammer scan the skyline of Foggy Bottom from the roof of Strong Hall, 1948 ca. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Photograph: Mary Brown and siblings standing on steps of house on Virginia Ave., NW, 1925 ca. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Photograph: Christine Duval Brecht, 1904 ca. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Photograph: Heurich brewery truck, 1910 ca. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Photograph: Duryea horseless carriage on Penn. Ave., NW, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Photograph: View of bank of Potomac River, home of Hazel Hanback, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Photograph: Historic map of early D.C., including Hamburg, 1795 ca. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Photograph: Washington Circle and Camp Fry, 1861 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Photograph: Houses on corner of 19th and F streets, NW, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Photograph: Inauguration of the Clark Mills statue of George Washington on Washington Circle, 02/22/1860 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Banner: 90 Years in Foggy Bottom, 02/2002 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Button: Historic Foggy Bottom, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Photograph: Planting anchor trees at Tompkins Hall, 1956 ca. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Photograph: Two children in a wagon by the Titanic Memorial, 1945 ca. (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Photograph: City block, 1925 ca. (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Photograph: Newly reconstructed ramp to the E-street expressway between near Rock Creek Parkway and Virginia Ave., NW, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residents, 1980 ca. (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residents, 1980 ca. (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Photograph: Pennsylvania Ave. and 20th street NW, Pepco building was here, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Photograph: View of area around F and 24th streets, NW, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Photograph: Association of Oldest Inhabitants of the District of Columbia, undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Photograph: Southwest corner of 19th and H streets, NW, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Photograph: "Spring-time redbud" near Francis Scott Key Hall, 04/1997 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Photograph: A view of Ohio Drive, 1946 ca. (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Photograph: Gethsemane Baptist Church and Rev. James Harvey (founder), undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Photograph: Foggy Bottom residents at a street festival held on I street, 1990 ca. (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Photograph: Demolishing the old Whitehurst freeway, 1995 ca. (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Photograph: Sunday School class at St. Mary's Episcopal Church at 23rd, between G and H streets, NW, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Photograph: St Mary's Congregation, 1940 ca. (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Photograph: Association of the Oldest Inhabitants of D.C. showing outside of building, undated (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Photograph: Area facing the Watergate complex, in the foreground is Va. Ave., 1950 ca. (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Photograph: A pre-renovation photograph of 826 25th street, NW, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Photograph: A view at the corner of 25th and I streets, NW, looking west, undated (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Photograph: The last house left at 23rd and G streets, NW, undated (Box 8, Folder 48)
    Site of GW's athletic facility, the Smith Center, built in the 1970s
  - Photograph: 20th street-19th street between E street and Virginia Ave., NW, 1950 ca. (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Photograph: Interior picture of St. Paul's Church taken at the Church's old location, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    Site of the old GW Hospital on Washington Circle
  - Photograph: Old Glass Works, 1850 ca. (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Photograph: Men in front of Leo's Deli, 1945 ca. (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Photograph: Mrs. Brecht, wife of Captain Theodore Brecht, 1910 ca. (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Photograph: Houses on 1908 H street, NW, 1925 ca. (Box 8, Folder 54)
    Site of Western Presbyterian Church
  - Photograph: World Bank Building, undated (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Photograph: GW hospital maternity ward, 1950 ca. (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Photograph: IMF building, 1980 ca. (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Photograph: Mrs. Gena Traver in front of her home at 2137 G Street, NW, undated (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Photograph: St. Stephen Martyr Church at 25th and Pennsylvania Avenue, NW, 1950 ca. (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Photograph: Aerial photograph of the George Washington University, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    Made by Dr. Daniel L.Borden
  - Photograph: Aerial photograph of 23rd street from Washington Circle, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Photograph: The Immaculate Conception Academy at 24th and K streets, NW, 1955 ca. (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Photograph: Former St. John's Orphanage, undated (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Photograph: Stott's Hall, 20th and I streets, NW, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Photograph: Entries in the St. John's Orphanage registry, undated (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Newspaper clipping: "Little Church Refuses to Sell to Monetary Fund", 11/10/1969 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Newspaper clipping: "Things Wont Be the Same West End Shopkeepers Sure Leases will Run Out as Building Continues", 05/20/1978 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Photograph: Various Shops, undated (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Newspaper clipping about Hamburg, and childbirths, undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Postcard of Watergate Gallery, undated (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Map of Foggy Bottom in 1972 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    2 copies, large and small
  - Map of Foggy Bottom in 1930 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Map of Foggy Bottom in 1933 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Photograph: View of Industrial Area along Virginia Ave., NW, 1920 ca. (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Foggy Bottom News clipping, 02/1958 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Photograph: Men with mugs of beer in hand at Heurich Brewery, undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Photocopy of Leo's Deli, undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Small poster of Washington Preparatory School and Marlow Coal Company, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Map of Potomac River bridges and inner loop expressway, undated (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Streets in Foggy Bottom, undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Poster of Young Men's Christian Association, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Map of South & North bound freeway and Pennsylvania Ave., undated (Box 8, Folder 82)